<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article article-type="article">
    <front xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
    <journal-meta>
        <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">advg</journal-id>
        <abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="full">Advances in Geometry</abbrev-journal-title>
        <issn pub-type="ppub">1615-715X</issn>
        <issn pub-type="epub">1615-7168</issn>
        <publisher>
            <publisher-name>Walter de Gruyter</publisher-name>
        </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
        <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">advg.7.4.529</article-id>
        <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1515/ADVGEOM.2007.031</article-id>
        <article-categories>
            <subj-group subj-group-type="subject">
                <subject code="PSB">Biochemistry</subject>
                <subject code="PSD">Molecular biology</subject>
                <subject code="PSF">Cellular biology</subject>
            </subj-group>
            <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                <subject>Protein Structure and Function</subject>
            </subj-group>

            <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                <subject />
            </subj-group>



        </article-categories>
        <title-group>
            <article-title>Groups of type <italic>L</italic>
                <sub>2</sub>(<italic>q</italic>) acting on polytopes</article-title>


                <trans-title xml:lang="fr">
                    <italic>Absorption des gaz polluants par le papier</italic>
                </trans-title>
                <trans-title xml:lang="de">
                    <italic>Die Aufnahme von Gasen der Umweltverschmutzung durch Papier</italic>
                </trans-title>

        </title-group>
        <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                <name name-style="western">
                    <given-names>Dimitri</given-names>
                    <x xml:space="preserve"> </x>
                    <surname>Leemans</surname>
                    <x xml:space="preserve">, </x>
                </name>
                <xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                </xref>
                <aff id="a1">
                    <label>
                        <sup>1</sup>
                    </label>Université Libre de Bruxelles, Département de Mathématiques - C.P.216, Boulevard du Triomphe, B-1050 Bruxelles.</aff>
                <email xlink.href="mailto:dleemans@ulb.ac.be" xlink:type="simple">dleemans@ulb.ac.be</email>
            </contrib>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                <name name-style="western">
                    <given-names>Egon</given-names>
                    <x xml:space="preserve"> </x>
                    <surname>Schulte</surname>
                </name>
                <xref ref-type="aff" rid="a2">
                    <sup>2</sup>
                </xref>
                <aff id="a2">
                    <label>
                        <sup>2</sup>
                    </label>Northeastern University, Department of Mathematics, 360 Huntington Avenue, Boston, MA 02115, USA.</aff>
                <email xlink.href="mailto:schulte@neu.edu" xlink:type="simple">schulte@neu.edu</email>
            </contrib>
        </contrib-group>
        <contrib-group>
            <contrib></contrib>
            <contrib />
        </contrib-group>
        <author-notes>
            <fn fn-type="com">
                <p>(Communicated by H. Van Maldeghem)</p>
            </fn>
        </author-notes>
        <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
            <day>19</day>
            <month>10</month>
            <year>2007</year>
            <string-date>October 2007</string-date>
        </pub-date>
        <pub-date pub-type="epub">
            <day>22</day>
            <month>11</month>
            <year>2007</year>
        </pub-date>
        <volume>7</volume>
        <issue>4</issue>
        <fpage>529</fpage>
        <lpage>539</lpage>
        <history>
            <date date-type="received">
                <day>24</day>
                <month>12</month>
                <year>2005</year>
            </date>
            <date date-type="rev-recd">
                <day>03</day>
                <month>07</month>
                <year>2006</year>
            </date>
            <date date-type="rev-recd">
                <day>06</day>
                <year>2007</year>
                <month>04</month>
            </date>
        </history>

        <copyright-statement>© Walter de Gruyter</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2007</copyright-year>
        <permissions>
            <license license-type="free">
                <p>This content is free.</p>
            </license>
        </permissions>
        <related-article related-article-type="pdf" xlink.href="advgeom.2007.031.pdf" xlink:type="simple" /><post-process status="nothing-found">2013-08-15T23:23:23.10345+02:00</post-process><original type="pdf" xlink.href="advgeom.2007.031.pdf" />
        <abstract>
            <title>Abstract</title>
            <p>We prove that if <italic>G</italic> is a string C-group of rank 4 and <italic>G</italic> ≅ <italic>L</italic>
                <sub>2</sub>(<italic>q</italic>) with <italic>q</italic> a prime power, then <italic>q</italic> must be 11 or 19. The polytopes arising are Grünbaum's 11-cell of type {3, 5, 3} for <italic>L</italic>
                <sub>2</sub>(11) and Coxeter's 57-cell of type {5, 3, 5} for <italic>L</italic>
                <sub>2</sub>(19), each a locally projective regular 4-polytope.</p>
        </abstract>
    </article-meta></front>
<body><sec sec-type="index_only"><p>Adv. Geom. 7 (2007), 529–539 DOI 10.1515 / ADVGEOM.2007.031  Advances in Geometry c de Gruyter 2007  Groups of type L2 (q) acting on polytopes Dimitri Leemans and Egon Schulte (Communicated by H. Van Maldeghem)  ∼ Abstract. We prove that if G is a string C-group of rank 4 and G = L2 (q) with q a prime power, then q must be 11 or 19. The polytopes arising are Gr¨ nbaum’s 11-cell of type {3, 5, 3} for L2 (11) u and Coxeter’s 57-cell of type {5, 3, 5} for L2 (19), each a locally projective regular 4-polytope.  1  Introduction  In this paper we determine the projective linear groups L2 (q), q a prime power, which occur as full automorphism groups of abstract regular polytopes of rank 4 (or higher). For groups of type L2 (q) there is a wealth of interesting constructions of regular polyhedra or maps on surfaces, but it is often assumed that q is a prime (see, for example, McMullen [16] or McMullen, Monson &amp;amp; Weiss [17]). There is also a considerable body of work available on representing L2 (q) as a group of orientation preserving mappings on surfaces, usually as the rotation (even) subgroup of the automorphism group of a regular or chiral polyhedron or map (see, for example, Glover &amp;amp; Sjerve [7] or Conder [2], as well as Section 6). Sjerve and Cherkassoff [23] determined precisely when a group L2 (q) is the full automorphism group of a regular polyhedron, thereby settling the existence problem when the rank is 3. In fact, the group L2 (q) may be generated by three involutions, two of which commute, if and only if q = 2, 3, 7 or 9. In other words, L2 (q) is the automorphism group of a regular polyhedron if and only if q = 2, 3, 7 or 9. In [23] it is also shown that the group PGL2 (q) may be generated by three involutions, two of which commute, for any q &gt; 2. Regular polytopes of rank 5 or higher cannot have an automorphism group of type L2 (q) (see Leemans &amp;amp; Vauthier [15]). This, then, leaves the case of rank 4. The purpose of this article is to prove the following theorem, which was conjectured in [15] and veriﬁed for q ≤ 61. Theorem 1. If L2 (q) is the full automorphism group of a regular polytope of rank 4, then q = 11 or 19.  530  Dimitri Leemans and Egon Schulte  In particular, it is found that there is just one regular polytope in each case. The 11-cell with group L2 (11) was constructed by Gr¨ nbaum in [8] by pasting eleven hemiu icosahedra together (see also [4]), and the 57-cell with group L2 (19) was discovered by Coxeter in [3]. For more details see Section 5.  2  Preliminaries  Abstract regular polytopes, string C-groups, and thin regular residually connected geometries with a linear diagram are basically the same mathematical objects. The link between these objects has been discussed in, for instance, McMullen &amp;amp; Schulte [18]. Here we take the viewpoint of string C-groups because it is the easiest and most efﬁcient one to describe abstract regular polytopes. As deﬁned in [18], a C-group is a group G generated by pairwise distinct involutions ρ0 , . . . , ρn−1 which satisfy the following property, called the intersection property: ρj | j ∈ J ∩ ρ j | j ∈ K = ρj | j ∈ J ∩ K for all J, K ⊆ {0, . . . , n − 1}.  We call n the rank of G. A C-group (G, {ρ0 , . . . , ρn−1 }), or simply G, is a string C-group if its generators satisfy the following relations: (ρj ρk )2 = 1 for all j, k ∈ {0, . . . , n − 1} with |j − k| ≥ 2. Each string C-group G then determines (uniquely) a regular n-polytope P with automorphism group G. The i-faces of P are the right cosets of the distinguished subgroup Gi := ρj | j = i for each i = 0, 1, . . . , n − 1, and two faces are incident just when they intersect as cosets. Formally, we also adjoin two copies of G itself, as the (unique) (−1)- and n-faces of P. Conversely, the automorphism group of a regular n-polytope is a C-group, whose generators ρj map a ﬁxed, or base, ﬂag Φ of P to the j-adjacent ﬂag Φj (differing from Φ in the j-face). Recall from [18] that {P1 , P2 } denotes the universal regular polytope (if it exists) with facets P1 and vertex-ﬁgures P2 . This covers every regular polytope with facets P1 and vertex-ﬁgures P2 .  3 The subgroup structure of L2 (q) We frequently require properties of the subgroup lattice of L2 (q). The subgroup structure of L2 (q) may be found in Dickson [6] (and was ﬁrst obtained in papers by Moore and Wiman). See also Huppert [12] for a weaker version. We mention the number of conjugacy classes of subgroups only for those subgroups employed in the proof of our main theorem. Theorem 2. The group L2 (q) of order q(q −1) , where q = pr with p a prime and r a (2,q−1) positive integer, contains only the following subgroups: 2  Groups of type L2 (q) acting on polytopes  531  1. elementary abelian subgroups of order q, denoted by Eq . 2. cyclic subgroups of order d, denoted by d, for all divisors d of 3. q(q2 −1) 2d(2,q−1)  (q±1) (2,q−1) . (q±1) (2,q−1) (q±1) d(2,q−1) is  dihedral groups of order 2d, denoted by D2d , for all divisors d of  4.  5. 6.  7. 8. 9. 10.  11.  with d &gt; 2. The number of conjugacy classes of these subgroups is 1 if odd, and 2 if it is even. q(q2 −1) For q odd, 12(2,q−1) dihedral groups of order 4 (Klein 4-groups), denoted by 22 . The number of conjugacy classes of these groups is 1 if q ≡ ±3(8) and 2 if q ≡ ±1(8). For q even, the groups 22 are listed under family 5. elementary abelian subgroups of order ps , denoted by Eps , for all natural number s such that 1 ≤ s ≤ r − 1. subgroups Eps : h, each a semidirect product of an elementary abelian group Eps and a cyclic group of order h, for all natural numbers s such that 1 ≤ s ≤ r and all pk −1 divisors h of (2,1,1) , where k = (r, s) and (2, 1, 1) is deﬁned as 2, 1 or 1 according as r r p &gt; 2 and k is even, p &gt; 2 and k is odd, or p = 2. For q odd or q = 4m , alternating groups A4 , of order 12. For q ≡ ±1(8), symmetric groups S4 , of order 24. For q ≡ ±1(5) or q = 4m , alternating groups A5 , of order 60. For q ≡ 0(5), the groups A5 are listed under family 10. q(q2 −1) w pw (p2w −1) groups L2 (p ), for all divisors w of r. The number of conjugacy classes of r r these groups is 2, 1 or 1 according as p &gt; 2 and w is even, p &gt; 2 and w is odd, or p = 2. groups PGL2 (pw ), for all w such that 2w is a divisor of r. Observe that when q is even, family 11 of Theorem 2 is a subfamily of family 10. The following lemma is also used very often in the proof of our result.  Lemma 1. ([12], S¨ tze 8.3 and 8.4) Let G = L2 (q) with q = pr , p a prime and r a a positive integer. Let M be a cyclic subgroup of order m in G. If M is a subgroup of q±1 a cyclic subgroup H &amp;lt; G of order h = (q−1,2) , then NG (M ) = NG (H) ∼ D2h and = therefore NG (M ) is a maximal subgroup of G.  4  L2 (q) acting ﬂag-transitively  In this section, we assume that G is a group isomorphic to L2 (q), with q = pr , p a prime and r a positive integer. Moreover, we assume that (G, {ρ0 , . . . , ρ3 }) is a string C-group of type {t, l, s} (i.e. the orders of ρ0 ρ1 , ρ1 ρ2 and ρ2 ρ3 are t, l and s, respectively). Clearly, t, l, s ≥ 3, since G is not a direct product of two non-trivial groups. As before we set Gi = ρj | j ∈ {0, . . . , 3}\{i} , for i = 0, . . . , 3. Our aim is to prove that q must be 11 or 19. We say that a subgroup H of G is an (irreducible) rank 3 subgroup of G if H is a rank 3 string C-group with a connected Coxeter diagram.  532  Dimitri Leemans and Egon Schulte  Observe that rank 3 subgroups must, by deﬁnition, contain dihedral subgroups of order at least 6. The next lemma is folklore but we provide a proof for completeness. Lemma 2. The dihedral group D2n of order 2n is not a rank 3 group. Proof. Suppose D2n is a rank 3 group with generators α0 , α1 , α2 (say). Then α0 α2 is an involution contained in the cyclic subgroup Zn of D2n and hence is the central element in D2n . Let Zn = β . Then α0 α2 = β n/2 , α0 α1 = β k for some k (with 1 &amp;lt; k &amp;lt; n), and α1 α2 = β n/2−k . Hence β 2k = (α0 α1 ) ∈ α0 , α1 and β 2k = β −2(n/2−k) = (α1 α2 ) −2 2  ∈ α1 , α2 , 2  but β 2k ∈ α1 . This contradicts the intersection property for C-groups.  Note that it is the intersection property that makes dihedral groups fail to be irreducible rank 3 string C-groups. On the other hand, a dihedral group can be the automorphism group of a regular map on a surface; however, these maps are not polyhedra in our sense (see [5, p.139]). By Theorem 2, the observation, and the previous lemma, the rank 3 subgroups of G are isomorphic to S4 , A5 , or L2 (q ′ ) or PGL2 (q ′ ) for some q ′ . These are the only possible types of subgroups for G0 and G3 . We begin with a sequence of lemmas aimed at eliminating L2 (q ′ ) and PGL2 (q ′ ) as possibilities. By inspection of the list in Theorem 2, we have: Lemma 3. The centre of a nonabelian subgroup of G has size at most 2. Moreover, if G has a nonabelian subgroup H whose centre has size 2, then q is odd and H must be a dihedral group. Lemma 4. The prime p must be odd. Proof. The subgroup G2 = ρ0 , ρ1 , ρ3 is a subgroup of the form 2 × D2t , with t as above. This subgroup is nonabelian and has a nontrivial centre. Hence by Lemma 3, it must be contained in a maximal subgroup of dihedral type of G and q must be odd. 2 From now on we may assume that p is odd. Lemma 5. The orders t of ρ0 ρ1 and s of ρ2 ρ3 must be odd. Proof. Let us prove, without loss of generality, that t must be odd. Suppose t is even. Then G2 ∼ 22 × Dt is nonabelian and |Z(G2 )| &gt; 2, a contradiction with Lemma 3. = Therefore, t (and s) must be odd. 2  Groups of type L2 (q) acting on polytopes  533  Lemma 6. Let H and K be two subgroups of type L2 (q ′ ) in L2 (q), with q ′m = q for some positive integer m. Then H ∩ K cannot be a dihedral group D2k with k &gt; 2 (and ′ ±1) k a divisor of (q 2 ). Proof. Let k &gt; 2, and let k be a divisor of 2  q′ ±1 2 .  By Theorem 2, we know that q(q2 −1) 4k  •  •  in L2 (q), there are qq(q ′2−1) subgroups isomorphic to L2 (q ′ ) and ′ (q −1) isomorphic to D2k ; ′ ′2 in L2 (q ′ ), there are q (q4k−1) subgroups isomorphic to D2k . (q′ −1) 2 −1) if k | (q 2 and n := ′  subgroups  Let n := q(q2 −1) 4n  (q′ +1) 2  +1) if k | (q 2 . By Theorem 2, there are  ′  subgroups D2n in L2 (q). Each subgroup D2n contains n subgroups D2k . Therek fore, each subgroup D2k is contained in exactly one subgroup D2n . The same kind of arguments show that each D2n is contained in exactly one L2 (q ′ ). Therefore, each sub′ ±1) group D2k of L2 (q) (with k &gt; 2 and k a divisor of (q 2 ) is contained in a subgroup ′ ′ L2 (q ) of L2 (q), and the number of subgroups L2 (q ) containing a given subgroup D2k is precisely one. Now the lemma follows. 2 Lemma 7. The subgroups G0 and G3 of G cannot be isomorphic to L2 (q ′ ), with q ′m = q for some positive integer m. Proof. Suppose, without loss of generality, that G3 ∼ L2 (q ′ ). Then the basic involution = ρ3 yields two conjugate subgroups L2 (q ′ ) of G whose intersection contains a dihedral group of order 2t; in terms of the underlying polytope, of which G is the automorphism group, each of these two subgroups is the stabilizer of one of the two facets which meet at the t-gonal 2-face in the base ﬂag of the polytope and are interchanged by the “involutory reﬂection” ρ3 . Then this intersection itself, being a subgroup of L2 (q), must be a dihedral group. However, this contradicts Lemma 6. 2 Lemma 8. Let H and K be two subgroups of type L2 (q ′ ) in L2 (q), with q ′m = q for some positive integer m. If H ∩ K contains a cyclic group Zk , k &gt; 2, whose normalizer NL2 (q) (Zk ) in L2 (q) is a maximal subgroup of L2 (q) of dihedral type, then H ∩ K ∼ = ′ (q′ −1) ∼ Z (q′ +1) when k | (q +1) . and H ∩ K = Z (q′ −1) when k | 2  2  2  2  −1) +1) +1) −1) Proof. As before, let n := (q 2 if k | (q 2 and n := (q 2 if k | (q 2 . For the normalizers in H and K, by Lemma 1, we have NH (Zk ) = NH (Zn ) = D2n and ′ ′ ′ NK (Zk ) = NK (Zn ) = D2n , where D2n and D2n are dihedral subgroups of H and K of order 2n, respectively, contained in the (dihedral) normalizer D := NL2 (q) (Zk ) (of ′ ′ order q ± 1), and Zn and Zn are their cyclic subgroups of order n. However, Zn and Zn ′ are cyclic subgroups of D of the same order, hence Zn = Zn ≤ H ∩ K. By Lemma 6, H ∩ K cannot be dihedral, so H ∩ K = Zn . 2  ′  ′  ′  ′  Lemma 9. The subgroups G0 and G3 of G cannot be isomorphic to PGL2 (q ′ ), with q ′2m = q for some positive integer m.  534  Dimitri Leemans and Egon Schulte  Proof. Suppose, without loss of generality, that G3 ∼ PGL2 (q ′ ). Then, by the same = argument as in Lemma 7, there are two subgroups isomorphic to PGL2 (q ′ ), namely G3 and Gρ3 , which are conjugate by ρ3 , and their intersection D must contain the dihedral 3 group D2t := ρ0 , ρ1 of order 2t. First observe that if m &gt; 1, there exists a subgroup L ∼ L2 (q ′2 ) such that G3 &amp;lt; L &amp;lt; = G. The element ρ3 ﬁxes D by conjugation, namely Dρ3 = D, and hence D ≤ L ∩ Lρ3 . Therefore, L ∩ Lρ3 itself must be a dihedral group, which contradicts Lemma 6. Hence we may assume that m = 1. Each of G3 and Gρ3 contains a subgroup of index 2 isomorphic to L2 (q ′ ). Since the 3 intersection of these two subgroups H and K (= H ρ3 ) cannot be dihedral by Lemma 3, it must coincide with a cyclic subgroup Zk of D of some order k. Then the normalizer of Zk in G is a maximal subgroup of dihedral type, since it contains D (and ρ3 ). By ′ ′ +1) −1) Lemma 8, we then know that k must be (q 2 or (q 2 ; that is, k = n, in our previous notation. On the other hand, since t is odd by Lemma 5 and the square of every element in D (and hence of ρ0 ρ1 ) is necessarily in H ∩ K (the index of L2 (q ′ ) in PGL2 (q ′ ) is 2), we also have t | n, that is, t | n = k. We claim that D is a dihedral group of order 4n. First recall that the maximal dihedral subgroups of PGL2 (q ′ ) are of order 2(q ′ ± 1) (see Moore [20]), so certainly D is of order 2n or 4n. Next observe that every subgroup D2n of G is contained in a unique subgroup D4n of G. This can be seen as follows. Clearly, every dihedral subgroup D4n of G contains exactly two dihedral subgroups D2n . Moreover, by item (3) of Theorem 2, the number of subgroups D2n in G is exactly twice the number of subgroups D4n in G. Hence, since every subgroup D2n of G actually is contained in a subgroup D4n of G, the latter must necessarily be uniquely determined, proving our claim. But now we can argue as follows. Assume that D is only of order 2n. Then D, viewed as a dihedral subgroup of G3 of order 2n, is contained in a maximal dihedral subgroup D′ of G3 of order 4n. Similarly, D, viewed as a dihedral subgroup of Gρ3 , is also contained in a 3 maximal dihedral subgroup D′′ of Gρ3 of order 4n. Hence, by uniqueness in G, 3 D ≤ D′ = D′′ ≤ G3 ∩ Gρ3 = D; 3 that is, D = D′ , of order 4n. This is a contradiction, so D must be of order 4n. Next we proceed by constructing a dihedral subgroup E in D of order 2t which is contained in H and K. This, then, forces H ∩ K to be dihedral and once again provides a contradiction to Lemma 6, thereby completing the proof. Let τ0 , τ1 be a pair of involutory generators of D with (τ0 τ1 )2n = 1. Since D contains ρ0 , ρ1 = D2t , we may assume that τ0 = ρ0 . Then (τ0 τ1 )2 ∈ H ∩ K but τ0 τ1 ∈ H ∩ K. Hence τ0 τ1 ∈ H or τ0 τ1 ∈ K. On the other hand, ρ0 ρ1 ∈ H ∩ K. However, ρ0 ∈ H and ρ0 ∈ K; in fact, if ρ0 is in H or K, respectively, then ρ0 = ρρ3 is in K (= H ρ3 ) or H 0 (= K ρ3 ) and hence τ0 = ρ0 ∈ H ∩ K = (τ0 τ1 )2 , which is impossible. Now suppose, without loss of generality, that τ0 τ1 ∈ H. Then, since τ0 = ρ0 ∈ H and H has index 2 in G3 , we must have τ1 ∈ H. It follows that the subgroup E := ρ0 ρ1 , τ1 of D must be a dihedral group of order 2t contained in H. We claim that E is also contained in K and hence in H ∩ K. For the proof we need to verify that τ1 ∈ K. Assume to the contrary that τ1 ∈ K. Then, since τ0 = ρ0 ∈ K and K has index 2 in Gρ3 , we must have τ0 τ1 ∈ K. 3  Groups of type L2 (q) acting on polytopes  535  Facet {5, 5}3 {5, 5}3 {5, 3}5 {5, 3}5 {5, 3}5 {4, 3}3 {4, 3}3 {3, 5}5 {3, 4}3 {3, 3}4  Vertex-ﬁgure {5, 5}3 {5, 3}5 {3, 5}5 {3, 4}3 {3, 3}4 {3, 4}3 {3, 3}4 {5, 3}5 {4, 3}3 {3, 3}4  Order of G 1 1 3420 60 1 96 24 660 1 120  Structure of G  L2 (19) A5 ∼ L2 (5) = 2 4 : S3 S4 L2 (11) S5  Table 1. Combinations of rank 3 polytopes  However, then K would contain the cyclic subgroup τ0 τ1 of order 2n, contradicting the ′ ±1) fact that the maximal cyclic subgroups of a group L2 (q ′ ) are of order (q 2 . It follows that τ1 ∈ K and hence E ≤ K, as required. This completes the proof. 2 We ﬁnally have all the tools to prove the following theorem, which in turn implies Theorem 1. Theorem 3. Let (G, {ρ0 , . . . , ρ3 }) be a string C-group. Suppose that G ∼ L2 (q). Then = q = 11 or 19. Proof. Lemmas 6 and 9 reduce the possible subgroups for G0 and G3 to only two kinds, S4 and A5 . The only rank 3 polytopes with group S4 are {3, 3} (= {3, 3}4), {3, 4}3 and {4, 3}3, and those with group A5 are {3, 5}5, {5, 3}5 and {5, 5}3. Recall here from [5] that {m, n}k is obtained from the regular tessellation {m, n} by identifying any two vertices that are separated by k steps along a Petrie polygon of {m, n}. Its group τ0 , τ1 , τ2 has a presentation consisting of the standard Coxeter type relations for {m, n} and the single extra relation (τ0 τ1 τ2 )k = 1. We can now check which pairs of polyhedra can be combined to form the facets and vertex-ﬁgures, respectively, of a regular rank 4 polytope. Table 1 gives the possible combinations and the structure of the corresponding “universal” groups; these groups are obtained by taking as deﬁning relations just those of the facet group and vertex-ﬁgure group as well as (ρ0 ρ3 )2 = 1. Only one from a pair of dual combinations is listed, since dual combinations yield the same groups (with the orders of the generators reversed). The results in this table can easily be obtained using a Computational Algebra package like M AGMA [1] (or, if necessary, by hand). Finally, by inspection we readily see that the only possibilities for (G, {ρ0 , . . . , ρ3 }) to be a string C-group of rank 4 occur when q = 11 or q = 19. 2 Note that the groups occurring in rows 1, 2, 5 and 9 of Table 1 are trivial. In row 4, the group actually is a group L2 (q) but is too small to be a C-group of rank 4. In row 7  536  Dimitri Leemans and Egon Schulte  we also do not have a C-group of rank 4. Finally, in row 6 we obtain a C-group of rank 4 isomorphic to 24 : S3 , namely the group of the universal locally projective regular 4polytope {{4, 3}3, {3, 4}3}. Given any type of group, the problem of determining whether or not it is the full automorphism group of a regular polytope is generally difﬁcult to solve due to the complexity of the subgroup lattice of the group at hand. However, for small groups, an atlas of their regular polytopes is available (see Leemans &amp;amp; Vauthier [15], Hartley [9]). For example, the Suzuki group Sz(8) admits regular polytopes, all of rank 3, while its automorphism group Aut(Sz(8)) = Sz(8) : 3 does not. In fact, the following more general result about almost simple groups of Suzuki type was obtained in Leemans [14]. Let G be a group such that Sz(q) ≤ G ≤ Aut(Sz(q)), where q = 22e+1 with e a positive integer. Then G is a C-group if and only if G = Sz(q). Moreover, if (G, {ρ0 , . . . , ρn−1 }) is a string C-group, then n = 3. Rephrased in terms of regular polytopes this result says that, among such groups G, only the Suzuki group Sz(q) itself can occur as automorphism group of a regular polytope of any rank, but does so only for regular polytopes of rank 3, that is, for abstract regular polyhedra.  5  The 11-cell and 57-cell  In terms of regular polytopes our main theorem can be rephrased as follows. Theorem 4. The only regular polytopes of rank 4 with automorphism groups of type L2 (q) are the 11-cell {{3, 5}5, {5, 3}5} with group L2 (11) of order 660, and the 57-cell {{5, 3}5, {3, 5}5 } with group L2 (19) of order 3420. The two polytopes of the theorem are self-dual and locally projective (see [18]); their facets and vertex-ﬁgures are regular maps in the projective plane. The 11-cell has 11 hemi-icosahedral facets, 11 vertices with hemi-dodecahedral vertex-ﬁgures, 55 edges, and 55 triangular 2-faces. (The hemi-icosahedron and hemi-dodecahedron, respectively, are obtained from the icosahedron or dodecahedron by identifying pairs of antipodal vertices, edges and 2-faces.) The edge-graph of the 11-cell is the complete graph on 11 vertices. The 57-cell has 57 hemi-dodecahedral facets, 57 vertices with hemi-icosahedral vertexﬁgures, 171 edges, and 171 pentagonal 2-faces. Each polytope is universal among the regular polytopes with the same kind of facets and vertex-ﬁgures. Moreover, in terms of their basic generators ρ0 , . . . , ρ3 , each of the groups L2 (11) and L2 (19) has a presentation consisting of the standard Coxeter type relations for the 3-dimensional regular hyperbolic honeycomb {3, 5, 3} or {5, 3, 5}, respectively, as well as the two extra relations (ρ0 ρ1 ρ2 )5 = (ρ1 ρ2 ρ3 )5 = 1 (the same two extra relations in each case). It is interesting to note the effect of dropping one, the ﬁrst (say), of the two extra relations just mentioned. For the type {5, 3, 5} we then obtain the universal regular 4polytope {{5, 3}, {3, 5}5} with automorphism group J1 × L2 (19),  Groups of type L2 (q) acting on polytopes  537  where J1 denotes the ﬁrst Janko group, a sporadic simple group of order 175560 (see [11]). This polytope covers the 57-cell. In [8], Gr¨ nbaum showed that there is no polytope of type {3, 5, 3} with icosahedral u facets and hemi-dodecahedral vertex ﬁgures (see also [10]). Hence, in that case, dropping one of the two extra relations still gives L2 (11). Recall that the even (or rotation) subgroup of a C-group consists of the elements which can be expressed as products of an even number of generators ρi ; it has index at most 2 in the full group. Note that, when considered as C-groups, L2 (11) and L2 (19) coincide with their even subgroups, because they are simple groups. The April 2007 Issue of Discover Magazine runs a popular article about the 11-cell written by Jaron Lanier (see [13]).  6  L2 (q) acting with two ﬂag orbits  Our main theorem can be rephrased as saying that there are just two abstract polytopes of rank 4 on which a group of type L2 (q) acts ﬂag-transitively as the full group of automorphisms. By contrast, there is a wealth of abstract polytopes of rank 4 on which a group L2 (q) acts with precisely two ﬂag orbits. In fact, this is already true in rank 3, the most prominent example being L2 (7), acting as the even subgroup of the automorphism group PGL2 (7) of Klein’s regular map {3, 7}8 of genus 3 (see [5], as well as [7]). The known examples of polytopes P with two ﬂag orbits generally have the property that adjacent ﬂags are in distinct orbits. This can arise in one of two ways. Either the polytope P is regular and L2 (q) is the even subgroup of its automorphism group (as in the case of the Klein map), or P is chiral and L2 (q) is its full automorphism group. (Recall here that an abstract polytope is chiral if its automorphism group has two orbits on the ﬂags, such that adjacent ﬂags are in distinct orbits.) One type of construction of examples of rank 4 begins with a 3-dimensional regular hyperbolic honeycomb and a faithful representation of its symmetry group as a group of complex M¨ bius transformations, generated by the inversions in four circles cutting o one another at the same angles as the corresponding reﬂection planes in hyperbolic space (see [22]). For example, for the regular honeycomb {4, 4, 3}, the even subgroup of its symmetry group is isomorphic to L2 (Z[i]) : 2, where Z[i] is the ring of Gaussian integers. Then interesting ﬁnite regular or chiral polytopes P of rank 4 can be obtained by modular reduction of this group. In each case, the resulting group is of type L2 (R), with R a ﬁnite ring, and acts as a group of automorphisms of P with two ﬂag orbits. In certain cases, R is a ﬁeld. For example, if p is a prime with p ≡ 3(4), then P is regular, the even subgroup is L2 (p2 ), and P has toroidal facets {4, 4}(p,0) and cubical vertex-ﬁgures {4, 3} (see [22, p.238]). Similarly, if p is a prime with p ≡ 1(8), then P is chiral, the automorphism group is L2 (p), and P has toroidal facets {4, 4}(b,c), with b2 + c2 = p, and again cubical vertex-ﬁgures {4, 3} (see [22, p.239]). There are similar such results for other Schl¨ ﬂi a symbols (see also [21]). Yet more examples of polytopes with two ﬂag orbits can be found in, for instance, [19].  538  Dimitri Leemans and Egon Schulte  Acknowledgement. This research was accomplished while the ﬁrst author was visiting the second author at Northeastern University. The ﬁrst author gratefully acknowledges ﬁnancial support from the Belgian National Fund for Scientiﬁc Research, the “Fondation Agathon De Potter” from the “Classe des Sciences” of the “Acad´ mie Royale de e Belgique”, and the “Communaut´ Francaise de Belgique - Actions de Recherche Cone ¸ cert´ es”. The second author was supported by NSA-grant H98230-05-1-0027. e The authors also thank the anonymous referees for some helpful comments.  References [1] W. Bosma, J. Cannon, C. Playoust, The Magma algebra system. I. The user language. J. Symbolic Comput. 24 (1997), 235–265. MR1484478 Zbl 0898.68039 [2] M. Conder, Hurwitz groups: A brief survey. Bull. Amer. Math. Soc. (N.S.) 23 (1990), 359–370. MR1041434 (91d:20032) Zbl 0716.20015 [3] H. S. M. Coxeter, Ten toroids and ﬁfty-seven hemidodecahedra. Geom. Dedicata 13 (1982), 87–99. MR679218 (84e:52011) Zbl 0506.51016 [4] H. S. M. Coxeter, A symmetrical arrangement of eleven hemi-icosahedra. In: Convexity and graph theory (Jerusalem, 1981), volume 87 of North-Holland Math. Stud., 103–114, NorthHolland 1984. MR791020 (86h:52005) Zbl 0569.52010 [5] H. S. M. Coxeter, W. O. J. Moser, Generators and relations for discrete groups. Springer 1980. MR562913 (81a:20001) Zbl 0422.20001 [6] L. E. Dickson, Linear groups: With an exposition of the Galois ﬁeld theory. Dover Publications Inc., New York 1958. MR0104735 (21 #3488) Zbl 0082.24901 [7] H. Glover, D. Sjerve, Representing PSl2 (p) on a Riemann surface of least genus. Enseign. Math. (2) 31 (1985), 305–325. MR819357 (87a:20051) Zbl 0594.30046 [8] B. Gr¨ nbaum, Regularity of graphs, complexes and designs. In: Probl` mes combinatoires et u e th´ orie des graphes (Colloq. Internat. CNRS, Univ. Orsay, Orsay, 1976), volume 260 of Cole loq. Internat. CNRS, 191–197, CNRS, Paris 1978. MR539975 (81f:05060) Zbl 0419.05017 [9] M. I. Hartley, An atlas of small regular polytopes. Period. Math. Hungar. 53 (2006), 149–156. MR2286467 (2007i:51027) [10] M. I. Hartley, An exploration of locally projective polytopes. Preprint. [11] M. I. Hartley, D. Leemans, Quotients of a universal locally projective polytope of type {5, 3, 5}. Math. Z. 247 (2004), 663–674. MR2077414 (2005c:51020) Zbl 1071.51013 [12] B. Huppert, Endliche Gruppen. I. Springer 1967. MR0224703 (37 #302) Zbl 0217.07201 [13] J. Lanier, Jaron’s world: shapes in other dimensions. Discover Magazine, April 2007 Issue, 28–29. [14] D. Leemans, Almost simple groups of Suzuki type acting on polytopes. Proc. Amer. Math. Soc. 134 (2006), 3649–3651. MR2240679 (2007e:52016) [15] D. Leemans, L. Vauthier, An atlas of abstract regular polytopes for small groups. Aequationes Math. 72 (2006), 313–320. MR2282877 [16] P. McMullen, Regular polyhedra related to projective linear groups. Discrete Math. 91 (1991), 161–170. MR1124763 (92f:52023) Zbl 0746.52016  Groups of type L2 (q) acting on polytopes  539  [17] P. McMullen, B. Monson, A. I. Weiss, Regular maps constructed from linear groups. European J. Combin. 14 (1993), 541–552. MR1248062 (94j:52019) Zbl 0820.51017 [18] P. McMullen, E. Schulte, Abstract regular polytopes. Cambridge Univ. Press 2002. MR1965665 (2004a:52020) Zbl 1039.52011 [19] B. Monson, A. I. Weiss, Regular 4-polytopes related to general orthogonal groups. Mathematika 37 (1990), 106–118. MR1067892 (91k:52021) Zbl 0689.51008 [20] H. E. Moore, The subgroups of the generalized ﬁnite modular group. Chicago, the decennial publications 1903. JFM 34.0172.02 [21] B. Nostrand, E. Schulte, Chiral polytopes from hyperbolic honeycombs. Discrete Comput. Geom. 13 (1995), 17–39. MR1300507 (95h:52016) Zbl 0820.51018 [22] E. Schulte, A. I. Weiss, Chirality and projective linear groups. Discrete Math. 131 (1994), 221–261. MR1287736 (95g:52016) Zbl 0806.52010 [23] D. Sjerve, M. Cherkassoff, On groups generated by three involutions, two of which commute. In: The Hilton Symposium 1993 (Montreal, PQ), volume 6 of CRM Proc. Lecture Notes, 169–185, Amer. Math. Soc. 1994. MR1290589 (95h:20039) Zbl 0818.20035 Received 24 December, 2005; revised 3 July, 2006 and 6 April, 2007 D. Leemans, Universit´ Libre de Bruxelles, D´ partement de Math´ matiques - C.P.216, Boulevard e e e du Triomphe, B-1050 Bruxelles Email: dleemans@ulb.ac.be E. Schulte, Northeastern University, Department of Mathematics, 360 Huntington Avenue, Boston, MA 02115, USA Email: schulte@neu.edu  </p></sec></body></article>